RG 004:083, Middletown Probate Court
Connecticut State Library
Middletown Probate Court records
1752-1936
Connecticut State Library
Connecticut. Probate Court (Middletown District)
52.75 cubic feet
Record books, 1752-1759; Probate files, 1752-1932. Index to and applications for commitments, 1870-1936.
RG004_083
1916-005, 1934-002, 1980-041, 1981-001.
Historical Note
Middletown, Middlesex County, Town established September 11, 1651, named November 1653, City incorporated May 1784
The Middletown District was constituted May 1752, from the East Haddam, Guilford, and Hartford Probate Districts. The Middletown Probate District serves the municipalities of Cromwell, Durham, Middlefield, and Middletown. It also served the following municipalities at various times: Berlin, May 1785 - June 1, 1825 (part taken from Middletown); East Hampton (Chatham), October 1767 - May 31, 1824 (area north of Salmon River); Haddam, May 1752 - June 2, 1830.
City of Middletown, Probate District chronology:
September 1651 - May 1666, Hartford Colonial Jurisdiction
May 1666 - May 1752, Hartford County Court & District
October 1741 - May 1752, East Haddam District (Covered that part of Middle Haddam Society lying in Middletown)
May 1742 - October 1767, East Haddam District (Covered that part of town lying south of Salmon River which became the Town of Chatham October 1767; these records are included with those of the Colchester Probate District)
May 1666 - May 1752, Hartford County Court & District
May 1752 - Present, Middletown District
For Probate Court contact information and hours of operation see,.
Scope and Content
Probate record books, 1752-1759. Volume 1 only. Contact the probate court to access record books after Volume 2. See Alternative Form Available note below.
Probate files, 1752-1932. Probate files may consist of estates, conservatorships, guardianships, commitments, and insolvencies. See Alternative Form Available note below.
Inventory control book, 1752-1831 (coverage). Also known as the Godard Digest, it is a list of probate files transferred to the Connecticut State Library. It was compiled at the Connecticut State Library under the direction of State Librarian George S. Godard.
Index to and application for commitments, 1870-1936, are for Connecticut State Hospital.
Arrangement
Probate files in accession 1916-005 are arranged alphabetically in one series.
Probate files in accession 1980-041 are arranged alphabetically.
Index to commitments and applications for commitments in accession 1981-001 are arranged alpabetically.
Other Finding Aid
Probate Files: The Probate Estate Papers Index, located in the index corridor adjacent to the History and Genealogy Reading Room, has two parts, a general index covering most of the state, and a Hartford Probate District index covering Hartford and some surrounding towns, 1820-1920. The index cards are arranged alphabetically by individual's last name and first names. The cards have the individual's name, town of residence, probate district, and list of items contained in the estate packet. To request retrieval of an estate packet, copy at least the estate name, file date, and probate district name from the index card. The probate files in Accession 1916-005 and Accession 1980-041 are represented in this index. Files in accession 1980-041 are listed on white cards.
Index Terms
Subjects:
Probate records -- Connecticut -- Berlin; Probate records -- Connecticut -- Cromwell; Probate records -- Connecticut -- Durham; Probate records -- Connecticut -- East Hampton; Probate records -- Connecticut -- Haddam; Probate records -- Connecticut -- Middlefield; Probate records -- Connecticut -- Middletown
Places:
Berlin (Conn.); Cromwell (Conn.); Durham (Conn.); East Hampton (Conn.); Haddam (Conn.); Middlefield (Conn.); Middletown (Conn.)
Restrictions on Access
Researchers should first consult use copies when available. See Alternate Form Available Section below.
Probate files from 1921-1932 are RESTRICTED as they may contain confidential documents. Tax returns (succession, transfer and estate tax returns and all attachments) from January 1, 1921 and later are confidential per Connecticut General Statutes §12-15.
See the policy.
Alternative Form Available
Record books, volumes 1-18, 20, 22, 24-25, 28, 32-33, 35, 37, 40-41, 44-46, 48-49, 52-54, 57, 61, 64, 66 1752-1917; probate files, 1752-1932; and inventory control book (Godard Digest) were microfilmed by the Genealogical Society of Utah and are available for use in the History and Genealogy reading room or through the. Volume 29 was missing and not filmed.
Provenance
The record book in accession 1934-002 was transferred to the Connecticut State Library on November 14, 1934.
The probate files in accession 1916-005 were transferred to the Connecticut State Library on the following dates (with date span of files): October 24, 1916 (1752-1831).
The probate files in accession 1980-041 were transferred to the Connecticut State Library on September 25, 1980 and October 3, 1980.
The index to commitments and application for commitments in accession 1981-001 were transferred to the Connecticut State Library on May 13, 1981.
Container List
- Record books, 1752-1759; .25 cubic feet (1 volume); 1934-002
  - Records, 1752-1759 (Volume 1)
- Probate files, 1752-1831; 12 cubic feet; 1916-005
  - Abbe - Ball (Drawer 1)
  - Banks - Burr, D. (Drawer 2)
  - Burr, E. - Comstock (Drawer 3)
  - Cone - Exton (Drawer 4)
  - Fairbanks - Hand (Drawer 5)
  - Harding - Johnson, R. (Drawer 6)
  - Johnson, S. - Miller, S. (Drawer 7)
  - Miller, T. - Ranney (Drawer 8)
  - Ransom - Seward, M. (Drawer 9)
  - Seward, N. - Stowe, E. (Drawer 10)
  - Stowe, F. - Ward, T. (Drawer 11)
  - Ward, U. - Z.; Miscellaneous (Drawer 12)
- Inventory Control Book, 1752-1831; T003073
  Index of the four accessions of probate files now merged into accession 1916-005
  Date span is coverage
  Also known as the Godard Digest
- Probate files, 1817-1932; 33.5 cubic feet; 1980-041
  - Abbey - Alsop, C. (Drawer 1)
  - Alsop, E. - Arnold (Drawer 2)
  - Ashton - Bacon, C. (Drawer 3)
  - Bacon, D. - Bailey, Ezra (Drawer 4)
  - Bailey, Ezra - Baldwin (Drawer 5)
  - Ball - Bell (Drawer 6)
  - Bellman - Birdsey, J. (Drawer 7)
  - Birdsey, L. - Boardman (Drawer 8)
  - Bolles - Brennan (Drawer 9)
  - Brewer - Burke (Drawer 10)
  - Burns - Camp, A. (Drawer 11)
  - Camp,C. - Cary (Drawer 12)
  - Case - Clark, D. (Drawer 13)
  - Clark, E. - Coe, Charlotte (Drawer 14)
  - Coe, Chauncey - Cohen (Drawer 15)
  - Coit - Cooke (Drawer 16)
  - Cooley - Cromwell (Drawer 17)
  - Cronin - Daniels (Drawer 18)
  - Darrow - Dickinson (Drawer 19)
  - Dickson - Dugan (Drawer 20)
  - Dunham - Edwards, Laura (Drawer 21)
  - Edwards, Lenas - Faxon (Drawer 22)
  - Fenn - Foster, William (Drawer 23)
  - Foster Mfg. Co. - Gardner (Drawer 24)
  - Garrison - Glynn (Drawer 25)
  - Godfrey - Griffith (Drawer 26)
  - Griswold - Hall, Jonathan (Drawer 27)
  - Hall, Julia - Harris (Drawer 28)
  - Harrison - Higginson (Drawer 29)
  - Hill - Hubbard, Elihu (Drawer 30)
  - Hubbard, Elijah - Hubbard, Josiah (Drawer 31)
  - Hubbard, Julia - Hull, H. (Drawer 32)
  - Hull, J. - Jewett (Drawer 33)
  - Johnson, A. - Johnson, R. (Drawer 34)
  - Johnson, S. - Kling (Drawer 35)
  - Knapps - L'Hommedieu (Drawer 36)
  - Lincoln - Lyman, A. (Drawer 37)
  - Lyman, C. - Lyman, Harriet (Drawer 38)
  - Lyman, Henry - McKinley (Drawer 39)
  - McKinstry - Meigs (Drawer 40)
  - Melander - Miller, I. (Drawer 41)
  - Miller, J. - Mowry (Drawer 42)
  - Mulcahey - Newton (Drawer 43)
  - New York & Boston Railroad Co. - O'Donnell (Drawer 44)
  - Ogden - Parmalee, B. (Drawer 45)
  - Parmalee, C. - Parsons, Samuel (Drawer 46)
  - Parsons, Samuel H. - Peters (Drawer 47)
  - Pike - Prout, F. (Drawer 48)
  - Prout, H. - Roberts, Adonijah (Drawer 49)
  - Roberts, Alfred - Rockwell (Drawer 50)
  - Rogers - Ryan (Drawer 51)
  - Sage - Savage, Josiah (Drawer 52)
  - Savage, Josiah - Sears (Drawer 53)
  - Sebor - Smith, Albert (Drawer 54)
  - Smith, Alfred - Smith, Winthrop (Drawer 55)
  - Solger - Starr, G. (Drawer 56)
  - Starr, H. - Stocking, E. (Drawer 57)
  - Stocking, H. - Sutton (Drawer 58)
  - Swaddle - Tidgewell (Drawer 59)
  - Tieman - Turner, E. (Drawer 60)
  - Turner, F. - Ward, Elijah (Drawer 61)
  - Ward, Eliza - Watkinson (Drawer 62)
  - Watrous - Whitmore (Drawer 63)
  - Whittlesey - Wilcox, R. (Drawer 64)
  - Wilcox, S. - Wirth (Drawer 65)
  - Wolcott - Zimmerer (Drawer 66)
  - Adoptions and insanity files (Drawer 67)
- Index to and applications for commitments, 1870-1936; 7 cubic feet; 1981-001
  - Index to commitments to Connecticut State Hospital
    - A-K (Box 1)
    - K-Z (Box 2)
  - Applications for commitments to Connecticut State Hospital
    - A-C (Box 3)
    - D-H (Box 4)
    - I-M (Box 5)
    - N-S (Box 6)
    - T-Z (Box 7)